Guide to the Francis Gilman Blake Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Francis Gilman Blake papers
1908-1953
MS 1281
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
9
(16 boxes)
The papers consist of laboratory notebooks, lecture notes, patient charts, correspondence and photographs, primarily documenting the medical career of Francis Gilman Blake, including his tenure as Dean of the Yale School of Medicine and medical research. Also included is correspondence to his wife documenting his personal life.
Blake, Francis G. (Francis Gilman), 1887-1952
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Yale University Historical Medical Library, 1980. Gift of John B. Blake, 2006.
Biographical / Historical
Francis Gilman Blake was born on February 22, 1887, in Mansfield Valley, Pennsylvania. After his father died when he was three, his family moved to Massachusetts. He received his A.B. from Dartmouth in 1908 and spent the next year tutoring a schoolboy in Maine in order to pay for Harvard Medical School, from which he received his M.D. in 1913. For the next three years, Blake worked as an intern at Peter Bent Brigham Hospital. He met Dorothy P. Dewey, a nurse in training at Peter Bent Brigham, whom he married on June 1, 1916, and with whom he had three sons. Over the next few years, Blake worked as a researcher at the Rockefeller Institute and as a professor of medicine at the University of Minnesota. In 1921, he joined the faculty at the Yale School of Medicine as one of the youngest full professors of medicine in the school's history. He served as dean of the school from 1940 to 1947. His important contributions to the medical field include research in epidemic diseases and some of the first laboratory and clinical tests of penicillin. Throughout his life, Blake was associated with the government and army, serving as civil director of army medical research. He died of a heart condition at Walter Reed Hospital in Washington, on February 1, 1952.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of laboratory notebooks, lecture notes, patient charts, correspondence and photographs, primarily documenting the medical career of Francis Gilman Blake, including his tenure as Dean of the Yale School of Medicine and medical research. Also included is correspondence to his wife documenting his personal life.
Medicine; Blake, Francis G. (Francis Gilman), 1887-1952
- Inventory
  - Laboratory books, lecture notes, research material, photographs, charts, and correspondence relating to medical research, 1908-1950 (Box 1)
  - Laboratory books, lecture notes, research material, photographs, charts, and correspondence relating to medical research, 1908-1950 (Box 2)
- Additional Material, 1910-1953; Accession 2006-M-125
  Arrangement
  The accession has been arranged into four sections: Academic Files, Office Files, Personal Files and United States of America Typhus Commission and alphabetical by title therein.
  - Academic Files
    - Dartmouth College
      - Class of 1908 reports, 1911-1924 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Class reunions brochures and correspondence, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Honorary degree: correspondence and event ephemera, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Harvard Medical Alumni Association: correspondence, publications, and event ephemera, 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Harvard Medical School: correspondence, publications, and memorabilia, 1910-1913 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Lectures
      - Unpublished manuscripts, 1922-1951 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Wadsworth, Augustus B., Lecture: correspondence, drafts, contracts, and ephemera, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Office Files
    - Advisory Council on Medical Education correspondence, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1948-1950 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - American College of Physicians
      - Correspondence, brochures, and ephemera, 1942-1949 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
      - Event ephemera, 1930-1931 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - American Geographical Society, 1944-1951 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - American Medical Association
      - Memorabilia and publications, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Publications and correspondence, 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - American Philosophical Society, 1952-1951 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - American Red Cross, 1945-1950 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Army Epidemiological Board, Circa 1949 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Association of American Physicians correspondence and memorabilia
      - 1933-1939 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - 1947-1949 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Australian Postgraduate Federation in Medicine, 1950-1951 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    - Beaumont Club, 1947-1951 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Blood Characterization and Preservation Laboratory, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Brookhaven National Laboratory, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - "Celebration of Medical Progress at the University of Pennsylvania" correspondence and event ephemera, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Columbia University College of Physicians and Surgeons correspondence, 1944-1947 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Committee on Post-War Medical Service correspondence, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Connecticut War Council correspondence and ephemera, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Consultation, Cairo, Egypt: press release and photograph, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Cornell University Medical College correspondence, 1939-1942 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Disease research and publications correspondence, 1943-1945 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - "European Sojourn": family writings, ephemera, and newsclipping, 1926-1927 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Funk and Wagnall's New Standard Encyclopedia Consulting and Advisory Board, 1948-1949 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - General correspondence
      - Medical publications, 1946-1950 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - Medical research and events, 1935-1937 (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - Medical research and miscellaneous topics, 1939-1942 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Harvard University
      - Board of Overseers, 1944-1950 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - Medical School correspondence and event ephemera, 1934-1949 (Box 3, Folder 19-21)
        General
        Includes Tercentenary ephemera.
    - Interurban Clinical Club, 1947, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - James Walker Memorial Hospital correspondence, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Johns Hopkins Hospital correspondence
      - 1933 (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - 1939-1942 (Box 3, Folder 25)
      - 1946-1948 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Journal of Immunology, 1948-1951 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Lasker Award, 1946-1947 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Life Insurance Medical Research Fund, 1944-1951 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Medical conference brochures, programs, and event ephemera
      - 1919-1940 (Box 4, Folder 2-5)
      - 1941-1947 (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
    - Merck & Co., Inc., 1948-1951 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - National Academy of Sciences, 1946 May 8-1951 November (Box 5, Folder 5-6)
    - National Advisory Health Council, general, 1947-1951 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - National Blood Program, 1948-1951 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - National Committee for Mental Hygiene correspondence, 1932 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - National Research Council
      - Correspondence, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - Correspondence, fellowship report, and newsclipping, 1932-1936 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - Streptococcal infection conference for U.S. Navy, 1945 July 6-7 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - Subcommittee on Infectious Diseases minutes, 1933-1944 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - New England Journal of Medicine correspondence, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - New Haven Hospital pamphlets and ephemera, 1931 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - New York Academy of Medicine, 1945 September-1947 November (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Office of Research and Scientific Development correspondence, 1944-1946 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Peter Bent Brigham Hospital correspondence, ephemera, newspaper clippings and publication
      - 1914-1919 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - 1933-1938 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Peters, John, Dr., 60th birthday event ephemera and correspondence, 1937 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Postgraduate Medicine, Medical Advisory Board, 1945-1950 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Research and Development Board, 1948-1951 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Rhode Island Medical Society correspondence and publications, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Rockefeller Foundation correspondence, 1943-1946 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research correspondence
      - 1919-1920 (Box 6, Folder 12)
      - 1933-1940 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Scarlet fever research newspaper clippings, 1924-1925 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Trip to Central America correspondence and memorabilia, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - United States Public Health Service clearance documents and correspondence, 1944-1948 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - University of Aberdeen correspondence and newspaper clipping, 1934, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - University of Michigan School of Public Health correspondence, 1944-1947 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - University of Minnesota Medical School correspondence, publications, and ephemera, 1919 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - University of Pennsylvania School of Medicine correspondence, 1946-1951 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - War Department
      - Disease research: newspaper clippings, correspondence and ephemera, 1943-1945 (Box 6, Folder 21)
      - Office of the Surgeon General correspondence, 1946-1951 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - War-Time Graduate Medical Meetings correspondence, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Yale Institute of Human Relations publications and event ephemera, 1931 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Yale University
      - Correspondence, publications, and ephemera, 1920-1931 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Medical School
        - Correspondence, report, and publications, 1933-1937 (Box 7, Folder 3)
        - Office of the Dean correspondence, newsclippings, publications, photograph, and event ephemera
          - 1939-1942 (Box 7, Folder 4)
          - 1943-1945 (Box 7, Folder 5)
          - 1946-1951 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Yerkes Laboratories of Primate Biology, Inc., 1950-1951 (Box 7, Folder 7-8)
  - Personal Files
    - Correspondence
      - General
        - 1917-1922 (Box 8, Folder 1)
        - 1943-1944 (Box 8, Folder 2)
        - 1945 July (Box 8, Folder 3)
        - 1946-1951 (Box 8, Folder 4)
        - 1951 July 1-1952 January 31 (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - Colleagues in the Armed Forces, 1942-1946 (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - Consulting, 1947-1951 (Box 8, Folder 7)
      - Courtship and marriage, 1915 November-1916 June (Box 8, Folder 8)
        Includes newspaper clippings, wedding invitation, and memorabilia.
      - Dorothy Dewey (Blake)
        - 1916 (Box 8, Folder 9)
        - 1916 (Box 9, Folder 1-4)
        - 1917 March-June (Box 9, Folder 5)
        - 1918 February 13-1919 August 29 (Box 10, Folder 1-4)
          Scope and Contents
          During his tour of duty with the United States Army during World War I, Blake wrote frequently to his wife about the progress of his medical research. He discussed the conditions of his medical subjects, who were drawn from "detention centers", where new recruits were quarantined to isolate any contagions they may have brought with them to the base, the flora and fauna of the region, daily life at the bases where he was stationed (including maps of the base layouts), and the conditions of the hospitals where he worked.
        - 1919 December-1951 (Box 10, Folder 5-8)
        - New Guinea trip, 1943-1944 (Box 10, Folder 9)
          Correspondence betwen Blake and his wife details his research while working in New Guinea.
      - Letters of condolence and memorial ephemera on death of Francis Gilman Blake, 1952-1953 (Box 10, Folder 10-11)
      - Portrait of Blake for Yale, 1951 (Box 11, Folder 1)
        Includes ephemera.
    - Curricula vitae, bibliographies, and biographical information, 1924-1952 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Government personnel file, 1948-1952 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - United States Army record, 1917 December 11-1934 October 29 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - United States War Department authorization documents, travel papers, and receipts, 1941-1943 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - United States of America Typhus Commission
    - Award of Medal: correspondence, photograph, and War Department documentation, 1945-1946 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Clinical records, 1943 (Box 12, Folder 2-3)
    - Journal of research trip, 1943 September 22-December 18 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - New Guinea photographs, publications, and memorabilia, 1943 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Typhus research
      - Photographs, notes, and publications, 1943-1946 (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - Scrub typhus
        - Maps, publications, and research notes, 1944-1949 (Box 13, Folder 4)
        - Research data, reports, and publications, 1944, undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
        - Research notes, publications, and correspondence, 1944-1951 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Scrapbook of lecture tour to Australia and New Zealand, 1950 (Box 14)
    Includes material on return via Singapore, Bangkok, Karachi, Cairo, and London.